it's not a hallucination it's a fantasy
it's a fantasy of the user that the LM
can read your mind and know what it is
that that you wanted and to me I think
context is the key between where we are
today and where we want to go in the
future you might hire the world's best
SRE but when they join your organization
they don't know anything about your
organization so they don't know do you
run Windows in production re in
production Ubunto in production I think
a big missing piece here is the ability
to I'll call it normalize or make
legible what your infrastructure
actually looks like if you had enough
data then the LMS could make sense out
of that but because the data is not
public there isn't like a massive body
of data that they can come along and
identify all the loose strands that
connect different bits of data and the
data of one organization might not be
enough to satisfy
that you're listening to the AI native
Dev brought to you by Tesla
[Music]
hello everyone welcome back to the AI
native Dev today we're going to explore
a brand new horizon maybe of AI Dev
tools and how they apply to kind of
modern software development by going
into the world of devops and modern
infra and such basically few others can
be as well qualified to talk about that
than Armon dgar who is the co-founder of
Hashi Corp thanks Arman for coming here
onto the show talk to us about this yeah
thanks so much guy for having me looking
forward to it to start with we're gonna
dig into elaborate and built up this
sort of world of of devops sped a lot of
things with with terraform especially
when it comes to the cloud and how we
think about setting up modern infra
before we dive into AI itself maybe give
us a bit of a lay of the land of how to
think about managing or wrangling a
modern Cloud infrastructure today the
way I like to think about it is if we
take a step back from the specifics of
the tooling or the process and really
just think about what are the
fundamental steps in the life cycle of
managing infrastructure I think that's
important to understand because
ultimately that's the outcomes we care
about as opposed to the specifics of the
tooling or process so when I look at
that I think about day zero right you
sign up for an account with your
favorite hyperscaler you have to go set
up a foundation right so you need a
landing zone of your VPC your v-ets your
security groups your whatever so what's
that Landing Zone actually look like
that's Day Zero then you get to day one
where I have the blank Cloud environment
now I need to deploy my applications
into that a day one concern now you get
into day two where you say okay now I
have a bunch of existing apps running
now I have a patching action I have to
do there's a new Linux kernel version
that comes out okay so there's a day two
patch then I get to day three and now
I'm under scaling constraints so I need
to scale up or scale down or whatever
then you get to day four you have a
security incident whatever it is jdk
vulnerability I have to go do a bunch of
remediation on that and then ultimately
you're going to get to sort of Day end
of an application where now you're going
to decommission it right you have to
take it out of service so to me that's
how I like the thing about it there's
this sort of life cycle now there's many
techniques you can say I'm going to use
tools like infrastructure as code right
tools like terraform particularly
designed for things like that day zero
day one provisioning and the day ND
commissioning you have config management
tools Chef puppet anible they tend to be
more of day two day three Tools in terms
of hatching remediation config
management and then of course you have
other techniques like you could go
manually point and click you could use
the cloud provider by SDK whatever dire
so there's a bunch of techniques but
those life cycle points are fundamental
and I think that makes a lot of sense in
terms of the sort of the configuration
tools that get these changes applied to
it where would you classify in this
world the more the observability tools
or the the monitoring tools I guess they
they just later on top of that do you
feel like they fit that model yeah I
think they spand the whole thing right
so I think you take most observability
monitorial you're probably going to
configure them alongside the app that
got deployed day one right so I'm
deploying my app and I'm putting APM and
observability along with it and then I'm
going to operate that from day one
through to Day N right once I
decommission the app I'm probably not
monitoring it so I think it will span
that whole life cycle will be where
observability tools and you're probably
using tools like terraform to actually
deploy it at the same time as your
application gets deployed yeah I think
that makes sense and in general that's
probably true for all sorts of other
facets of it whatever cost controls that
you might have whatever security poster
management or other tools that you might
have post those yeah tools like whiz or
palto You' probably deploy again same
thing like day zero day one it's going
to live until Day end cost management I
think tends to be more of a day two day
three concern because until I've
deployed some of my I really know how
much cost so once I get into sort of
that day two day three it's hey I get my
cloud bill it's 30% higher than I expect
okay now I'm going to bring in some
finops tooling to figure out like why is
my spend higher than I thought so I
think that makes sense that's a useful
just starting point for us to talk about
what can we do then with AI and so we
built these different phases on it I
guess maybe for starters where do you
think AI is kicking in today to help
where have you seen it so today the way
I describe it I think is I'll introduce
a new term because we'll come back to it
a few times there's this notion of
almost context free Ai and what I mean
by that is I can go to Claude or GPT or
Gemini and say hey write me a terraform
script that will I don't know provision
let's say an S3 bucket and an ec2 VM and
so what I mean by that being context
free is I it it really doesn't need to
know anything about my existing
infrastructure I can go to a generic
Foundation model basically and just tell
it hey here's what I want and it can
spit out some reasonably terraform code
right I'd say at this point just given
based on pick your favorite modern model
it's going to be 90% pretty good in
terms of being able to write that
terraform code for you the flip side of
it right so that's I'll call it a
one-way translation from I have this
high level intent and that's translating
it to the implementation for me they're
also pretty good at going in the reverse
so I can give it an implementation and
say what's the intent right here's
20,000 lines of terraform code I don't
want to read it summarize this for me
what do you mean you want to read it
that's everybody's favorite favorite
activity to read exactly yeah and I
think there's value there because you're
a new engineer you just started at a
company you don't really know how it
works and so you're like hey I'm
supposed to manage this app as a
starting point I could sit there and
read the 20,000 lines or I could say hey
give me a high level summary of this
thing I'll say okay this is deploying a
Java app on an ec2 VM with an S3 bucket
and so I think the reason the tools are
very good at both those directions today
is you really don't need any context
Beyond either what's captured in the
user's intent to do the translation or
what's captured in the terraform code to
do the summerization you don't really
need to know anything else and so I
think for those relatively constraint
use cases there's a lot of value today
right in that day zero day one it can
give you a huge Head Start in writing
the initial code cut down the time it
actually takes and similarly to
summarize what's there it gives you an
understanding a lot faster right and in
this context it's infrastructure as code
is just code you don't really care if it
was Java or python it learns it it
understands it the same way how how do
you feel though I think it's interesting
to think about the distinctions between
infrastructures code and regular code
and so a few thoughts about that one is
infrastructures code tends to be an
extreme example in which you can write
things in very few lines in terraform
the complexity isn't in how many lines
it's just in understanding the
implications of what you just read what
how did you configure the VPC and all
that so it's not about complexity but
there's this like World of data or
understanding it's a very it's a
flammable environment right like or
combustible environment you could pretty
easily blow yourself up or your
environment how have you seen the the
level of knowledge of llms in this
domain and in general have there been
tools that you've seen around that maybe
help you grasp what is this seemingly
naive code that the L generated for you
but I think what's interesting and what
we've seen is I think one of the things
that's nice about in some sense the
conciseness of something like terraform
Cod and the very high declarative nature
of it means that there's really not a
lot of imperative logic that the llms
have to understand and what I mean by
that is if you give an llm a very
complicated function with lots of
branching lots of different sort of
conditionals unless you really know what
the execution flow is and what the data
path is it's hard to actually know what
the result is right because it's so
conditional and branching terraform code
tends not to look like that because it's
very flat it's very declarative that's
very limited in terms of like how much
branching you end up having and so in
that sense what's nice about is that
that flatness actually makes it a lot
easier I think for the LMS to understand
because they don't really need to reason
about data flow through the models or
through the execution path and so in
that sense I think they do a better job
potentially
yeah and and we see that I think in
terms of generating the code that you
intended many examples also in in tools
that are dedicated to trying to make the
LMS work better in which they represent
the requirement in a sometimes even
pseudo code or somehow simplified
language more metal language and
terraform is not far from pseudo code
but it is it is a meta language it is a
language that is above apis and so being
simpler makes it more likely there's
basically like slightly less options and
maybe you know but what about the the
implications of that and highlighting
those to the user if I'm writing Java or
I'm writing python or writing JavaScript
then first of all again I think I have
that's combustible but also I'm going to
write some tests I'm going to have some
of these defense mechanisms if I'm
setting up a VPC if I'm creating
infrastructure as code because I don't
have expertise in that space and I'm
using the llm to generate that and it
creates infrastructure to me how would I
know that it's now open for anybody to
access to me I think this highlights one
of the biggest risks we see is the model
really don't have a good sense of things
like what are the security implications
of these things what is secure by
default and what you can't expect from
them is that they're going to generate
things that are secure by default
necessary like you asked it for an S3
bucket it's probably going to generate a
public S3 bucket which might be what you
wanted but might not be what you wanted
and so I think that kind of a Nuance to
your point that combustibility here is
that's a oneline difference in
configuration whether you said private
is equal to true or private is equal to
false or you emitted it and it defaulted
to True right yeah so it's not the
difference between a bad thing happened
and a good thing happened is not the
number of characters being a lot or the
logic really being wrong it's just you
missed a declarative private equals true
and it had unintended consequences and I
don't think the models today they don't
really have a an appropriate semantic
understanding of the sort of security
boundary and security implication of
some of those things and so one config
field is the same as another could field
in terms of importance to them and I
think what's happening is you just get a
pattern match based on the input data of
if it's more S3 buckets that were public
than were private then that's what
you're towards that yeah yeah just
gravitating towards where the training
data which was like I saw more public
than I saw private so therefore I'm
defaulting public right that's the
nature of it and so I think part of I
think the answer of getting some of
these things right is to actually trust
some of the output I think you actually
need to invest in the right security
guard rails on the other side of it to
say okay how am I going to do automated
reasoning around that we think we talk a
lot about things like policy as code
which is okay if I'm going to let my
users write ter or generate terraform in
this case with AI I need to actually
have a set of policy card rails that I
trust that's the belt and suspender so I
might put a check that says okay you're
provisioning S3 bucket it has to be
marked private and so you might have
generated it but then I have a belt and
suspenders approach hey no you're just
asked for a public S3 bucket try again
and that becomes a user in the loop now
who has to go and say okay I'm G to
either I have to change my statement to
the El say make it a private S3 bucket I
need to be expli it or I'm just going to
modify the generated ter from code and
say private equals true I really like
how this is a bit of an extreme example
of something that is happening in code
that is not infrastructure as code as
well I just had Caleb SEMA on the
podcast and we had a bit of a
conversation about is generated code
secure and it's hard to make any sort of
strong statements about that part
because it's not one thing and we you
should go check out their episode if you
want hear everything we said about it
but what's interesting is you take these
questions and you take them to an
extreme it's easier to get a sense for
it and so in infrastructure code I think
I love that example around the S3 bucket
which which is it's not right or wrong
to create that S3 bucket it's public or
or private it's just about being
contextual we'll get to that but it's
also it's a decision and do you
understand the implications of it and
it's also easy to not notice the omitted
line or to not notice that it said true
or false and terraform is like an
extreme version of it that the same
types of omission exist in any other
programming language that you create but
they're just less evident or less
blatant or maybe and in all of those
cases the answer is code generation is a
part of your stack and all your software
elements but if you just assume that
code that gets generated is magically
fit for purpose especially when you
didn't even tell it to create a secure
bucket or a private bucket you just said
create me ans3 bucket then you have to
have other means of validating like
policy as code what is right and what is
wrong I think one of the interesting
things sometimes people ask me and say
isn't that just because whatever we
didn't write like if it had generated
unit tests for example for the terraform
that would have been CAU and my view is
no it's fundamentally unknowable because
what I don't know is maybe you're making
a marketing site and you're hosting
public assets like images and it should
be a public bucket or maybe this is
hosting customer data and it should be a
private but the problem is input was
fundamentally underspecified so there's
no way to know this is not a
hallucination it's just you
fundamentally underspecified your input
and so no amount of testing can tell me
whether it was right or wrong because I
don't I don't know what you wanted I had
a conversation side when we're saying
it's not a UC ination it's a fantasy
it's a fantasy of the user that the llm
can read your mind and and know know
what it is that that you want clearly a
Tesla we talk about spec Centric
development talk about creating a
specification and not just about prompt
but there's this good and bad thing
about specs in the llm era which is
whatever you don't say the llm will fill
in the gaps and you you need proper
tooling to be able to highlight too you
the decisions the llm has made you still
need to pay attention you still need
potentially policy's codes to to decide
whether it conforms to your company's
requirements or your own requirements
whatever whoever sets the rules you you
need some form of visibility to like it
or not the llm is going to fill in the
gaps and it's not going to Red your mind
while doing it well I think there's this
interesting tension to between sort of
under specifying and allowing the LM to
fill things in and when taken to the
Limit if you specify everything you're
effectively writing the terraform code
so another example I gave here is I said
I want an ec2 VM what OS is that ec2 VM
running is it Windows is it Red Hat
Linux is it Debian is it Ubuntu I didn't
specify but something's going to get
filled in the ec2m is going to be
running something so you will end up
with an operating system now you might
realize it wasn't the operating system
you wanted and so now you're going to
come back and be like give me an E2 VM
Running Red Hat Enterprise Linux with
this particular version and so you can
start to see then there's a whole bunch
of other things you didn't specify like
the size of the VM the region of the VM
the availabilities the VM and so the
more and more you start specifying it at
some point actually your declarative
input starts to converge on effectively
you're writing the terraform code so
there's this interesting balance here
how much can you leave unspecified
particularly in a world of
infrastructure where Details Matter
right if I'm asking it to write me a
Java code to sort a list as long as the
list is sorted do I really care not
really you might when your end gets
large enough and it turned out it was
bubble sore but I think in
infrastructure in particular the details
actually do tend to matter and so I
think this is where you start to run to
limits of context free generation the
other challeng maybe in the world of
infrastructure code is around the body
of knowledge to learn from and
infrastructure as code holds vast amount
of insight and guidance and you can see
these things but you really you don't
see implications when you just look at
the code it's what it did it's not
necessarily what was right what happened
to it and in code arguably because you
can run that code without operating you
can run the test there's been a lot of
Reliance by the LM companies of using
that data to train their system to
separate good code from bad or whatever
somehow prioritize it so that it's
properly encoded say prefer to generate
code in this fashion in infrastructure
as code or really in anything sort of
devops in modern infra I don't think
there is such a buddy of knowledge that
exists that is public information around
operability around what happened around
it failed to deploy a thing and how was
that remediated what were the cost
characteristics with were the
performance characteristics security
characteristics of something how do you
think about that do you think there is a
body of knowledge like that you think
can we is that a maximum limit that we
basically have to hit as an industry or
is there a way to solve this I so it's
interesting I think there's a bunch of
there's a bunch of different competing
factors here right on one hand I think
what's valuable is that there's a pretty
large community when we think around
terraform of people writing highquality
modules and sharing them publicly right
so in particular the hyperscalers
themselves will publish modules on how
to do Landing zones how to do common
patterns things like that so these are
sort high quality modules written and
curated by the cloud providers and
shared with their customers through
things like our public registry and
GitHub so you have a bunch of these
highquality curated examples that are in
the public domain at the same time I
think you have things like the terraform
registry where you have tens of
thousands of community maintained
modules and you have reasonable signals
of like how much they're useful and work
based on things like downloads version
history how often they're updated so you
can look at that and say okay I'm going
to look at the subset of things that are
frequently updated relatively recent
over a certain threshold of downloads
that signal they're a reasonable Quality
Bar and so you can subset the training
to a set of things that are known better
which is still a large body right tens
of thousands of examples yeah it's
sorting of the code like it's still code
you don't have further Insight but
you're relying on community insight to
help you rank which code should carry
more weight correct and then I think
even internally because of things like
terap Cloud we actually have more sort
of operational insight into hey we know
which terraform runs fail and succeed
for example and we know what code bases
and what what module versions that
correlates with so you can say okay I
know this one failed 10 times in a row
probably not a great example to learn
from versus other code base has a very
high success rate so those are higher
quality in some sense training data so
you can take some of that signal and
then use that to look and say okay I
have some inputs that I believe to be
higher quality in terms of what I want
to train on yeah so I think you have a
few of these different things that I
think helps pull that together but
you're right I think when you think
about the universe of maybe Java code
that's out there it's going to be a lot
bigger than infrastructure as code the
flip side is because infrastructures
code is I think a lot simpler more
constrained doesn't have complex
branching and data paths I think you
actually don't need probably as much
training data right and I think
similarly because the documentation is
so rich it also is a pretty valuable
form of training data versus
documentation for programming language
TS to be very lowlevel kind of function
oriented versus infrastructures code
tends to be resource oriented so the
documentation is actually a much richer
input source than it would be for a
programming language yeah and I tend to
agree with that I infrastructure as code
is an easier thing for llms to generate
the catch being it will successfully
generate working terraform code is it
creating the infrastructure that is
correct is a question that's harder
because in Java the it's it's easier to
run the code and see if it passed the
tests and in infrastructure as code it's
it's doable you could set up Cloud
environments and have those runs and for
all I know maybe a bunch of these llm
providers are doing some of that but
it's a lot more elaborate and expensive
and I'm curious because the cloud
providers themselves are so deep into
the llm foundation model providers as
well how much are they able or actually
are using the data that they see they
observe on their own platforms to be
able to guide it on one hand I'm sure
organizations will be plenty annoyed if
they do that on the other hand in a
position to see that I guess that's true
I'm not going to challenge you on those
for I guess that's also true with your
platform in a terraform Cloud so
interesting to see where it goes let's
talk about that's sort of step two
context free I generation and
summarization or sort of reading from it
is very useful has a bunch of caveat
about you still need to maintain your
sort of thresholds or policy of code for
responsible use of it probably
summarization it can be very good
because it has all the advantages and
none of the disadvantages we discussed
where do you see this headed where what
do you think is the next step yes I
think we alluded to it right here a few
times with this discussion on context
and to me I think context is the key
between where we are today and where we
want to go in the future which is the
example I would use and make this
concept a little bit maybe more crisp
for people is like you might hire the
world's best SRE who knows terraform and
Cloud inside and out but when they join
your organization they don't know
anything about your organization so they
don't know do you run Windows in
production real in production Ubunto in
production now they might be power users
at all of those things but the context
of knowing hey as an organization we've
standardized on real that's critical
piece of context that you have to be a
useful S at the or right you don't want
to hire someone to arrest my stack is
Windows and all of a sudden this
person's writing Linux for me it doesn't
help me right they need to understand
how does the organization work what have
we standardized on what does my existing
infrastructure look like for them to
generate things that are then
contextually relevant to my environment
and I think that's actually that context
if you think about it as that SRE who
knows about my environment or doesn't
know about my environment extends to
every point in the life cycle so even if
I go all the way to that day Zero
example I gave if I say just give me the
S3 bucket in the ec2 VM if the SRE had
the context to say okay what type of app
is this oh it's your production billing
app okay there's a few implications to
that production billing app probably
implies it should not be public so I
shouldn't have to specify S3 bucket is
public and if I standardize on real then
you're not going to ask me what's the
operating system because you I've
already standardized on real in some
sense the word assumption is an
important one here it's what are the set
of assumptions the llm is going to be
making that you want to make explicit
because you have context and that's
going to be everything from production
environments regulatory regimes like
billing app might need to be PCI
Compliant to operating systems that I'm
running to what regions I'm always in Us
East one or I'm always in whatever
region right so what are those things
that I need to have contextual awareness
that is going to let me be much more
effective in my day Zero and day one
when I'm doing that sort of generation
it makes very natural sense to want to
do those how much are you envisioning
this being more sit down and have an
interview with the Chief Architect to
understand this versus autodiscovery and
I guess it's a gutfield type question
but what level of granularity matters
here is it really just hey what are your
primary stacks and all that and the best
practices really amidst 99% of those
that use it and know what they're doing
is to do these things versus you really
the devils in the details you need to
understand this organization's micro
choices these interactions between these
applications and how they work to
achieve something that is comparable to
one of your good devops Engineers I
think for like the most of the things I
think that's a 8020 rule I think 80% of
the value is in codifying 20% of the
assumptions what I mean by that is like
for most people if it's cloud provider
it's region it's operating system it's
course like when you say give me a
database okay are we in my SQL shop or a
post shop right so I think it's probably
maybe a dozen key variables when you
think about like core stack that if you
say okay these dozen things I want to be
well aware of that probably is 80% of
sort of the surface area of what you
care about right that last 20% probably
starts getting super nuanced and
specific to each application so you
might say okay this is a highfrequency
trading app okay that has a whole bunch
of different very specific implications
because of the nature of that workload
but that workload is unique it to
probably doesn't represent most of your
workload most of my workload is three-
tier Java application so it's fine if
you make if you fill in some of the
blanks and it's doesn't matter but maybe
high frequency trade I really care about
performance latency sizing OS a bunch of
those variables will matter but it'll be
very workload specific and have you seen
anyone try to take this all the way to
go and say I will inspect all the
observability data and the terraform
State and whatever it is that I can
glean out of the deployed environment
that you have and how your application
operates and maybe historical data and I
will find you in a model I'm making this
but I will find you in a local model and
therefore I will generate perfect very
tuned but also attuned to your goals
you're looking to reduce costs so I will
make the choices around that I think
that sounds directionally like something
that a startup might do have you seen
companies or big incumbents take a crack
at doing things of that nature not quite
yet and I think maybe this gets into the
Second Challenge I think when we start
talking about context which is I think a
big missing piece here is the ability to
I'll call it normalize or make legible
what your infrastructure actually looks
like and and what I mean by that is if
you think about code great it's a flat
text file sitting in Version Control
that that that's all I need to know
about it it's all there if you think
about infrastructure it lives if you
will in some sense in the real world the
cloud World however you want to think
about it and so there's this sort of
running thing that's out there that has
all sorts of ephemeral attributes has
emergent properties because has
accumulated over decades and how do you
actually make that legible to an LL M
right and I think a big piece of what's
missing is the ability to inventory if
you will all of that in a consistent way
and then appropriately vectorize it
categorize it whatever so that then an
llm can reason about it in a structured
way right I think as humans we're really
good about dealing about with the
ambiguity of these environments and the
complexity of them but llms
fundamentally need to work on something
that's much more normalized like they
can't you can't tell them to go log into
the AWS console and click around and
figure out what production looks like
yeah maybe
in the you could yeah I think people can
do that and we should talk a little bit
about trust I think the blast rate is
there the combustibility comes back to
get in the way of that I I I like the
normalization question but I guess maybe
to challenge that a little bit like it
it is still small in comparison to like
parameters sort of the billions of
languages I guess in theory and maybe
that's the the dissonance here if you
had enough data then the LMS could make
sense out of that but because the data
is not public public there isn't like a
massive body of data that they can come
along and identify all the loose strands
that connect different bits of data and
the data of one organization might not
be enough to satisfy that I I think it's
actually worse than that it's not even
though the data is not public it's that
most organizations don't have it and
what I mean by that is I'll take a very
real example right open S vulnerability
and we work with thousands of
Enterprises the vast majority of them I
would say when they have an issue like
open us all vulnerability is you create
a spreadsheet and you go manually
inventory all of your applications and
then you go manually figure out what's
in production and then you manually
figure out what version of open ssls
there and then you go manually remediate
that so if you think about that's the
universe where most of these
organizations are starting with what is
the input to the llm yeah it's there's
just a bunch of stuff running in
production that's the start point
someone manually create that spreadsheet
but until you create that there was no
data for the it's just there's stuff
that is there it's an interesting almost
frustrating equation a little bit the
data technically exists it is in API
accessible systems we have a
technology competency that knows to take
fairly unstructured data and connect the
dots ownership of that data and
ownership to the access to that data
because maybe they would do the the leg
work is complicated and without it
getting like vast quantities of it you
you wouldn't be able to connect the dot
so you have to resort to this
normalization which in turn gets you
back to this no code land so you have to
anticipate all the variables and
something it really has too many
variables numerate so so I don't think
it's intractable I think to me it's like
how you have to solve this is in some
sense first of all we have to pull that
data and make it more queriable in a
sane way right meaning okay if I can
create sort of a representation that
says okay here is all my resources that
are running here's all the packages that
are running on those things here's the
versions of the application that are
running here's the I'm going to tag some
things production some staging some
development now I have a metadata that
says okay I understand applications I
understand environments I understand
what resources are associated with these
different things in some sense it's a
Knowledge Graph if I I can walk that
tree from okay from production to
application to these 50 VMS to the
packages on those 50 VMS I can start to
normalize that where now I have a
representation of this infrastructure as
opposed to it's just stuff running and
now that representation I can start to
answer an open-ended set of questions
right but it's I've normalized if you
will the what does my infrastructure
look like from it's just stuff that's
running into a knowledge graph that is
queriable and interactable by an llm in
a bit more of a structured way and so to
me I think that then starts to enable
that Foundation of context full and then
to your earlier point of how much am I
going to sit there and interview the
user and ask all them maybe the first 10
variables you'll ask them but the other
variables you'll infer them by mining
the knowledge graph so even operating
system if I look at the knowledge graph
and say hey 90% of it is running real
okay I can probably make an inference
that we've standardized on rail I don't
even need to ask the user but if I don't
have that graph and it's just here's VMS
I have no idea what's on those 50 VMS
how do you make that inference right you
have to know what's on the VM yeah and
so I think that's to me is once you have
that you can start to simplify the user
experience they don't have to enumerate
all their assumptions you can infer them
but also then the LM can do much more
advanced reasoning oh yeah application
fu is impacted by open SSL because we
can understand that the relationship
between these things exists ironically I
think if you have anywhere near that
type of information at your fingertips
you're already pretty good at managing
your modern infra like you're probably
quite up there so this might imply that
it's something that further extends the
Gap it fits more into the making the
ones that are good great versus dragging
along the ones that weren't as good at
least until such time that someone can
create an automatic thing that plugs
into all these apis and classify them
which frankly in security has been
happening with the world of csbm dbm all
of those a lot of them rely at least
from a from security poster perspective
which is only one lens on it but they do
rely on automated discovery of your
estate and classification and all of
that that are like roughly correct on
humans of course added them and two of
them so maybe that can have someone Jump
Ahead or sort of leap ahead from having
all that inventory to having AI
classification of that inventory on top
of which they can have ai workflows yeah
I think there's a lot of different
techniques there but I think it's about
pulling it together and then helping
these organizations frankly cross a
skills Gap that a lot of them have on
getting there because you're right if
you're an organization who had all of
this you're easily in the top percentile
I would say of organizations in terms of
maturity so how do you bring the rest of
that bell curve with you I think is the
problem and I guess maybe leaning a
little bit into that further future
which is the a Native because it give us
a picture of today of tomorrow but maybe
five years from now when we think about
something that is AI native I'm curious
what your thoughts are around like
autonomous devops some cases in which
you can actually have that that patching
process or something else be done
automatically how far do you think we
are from something like that do you one
is like crystal ball do you think this
is five years or is this 20 but also I
guess what would be deemed initial
successes around workflows that we can
say hey we are autonomously doing this
piece of modern infra handing right so
to me I actually I think there's
actually a few dimensions on which if
I'm looking at the five plus year
Horizon I think we'll see Evolution one
is I think in terms of the specification
level and what I mean by that is if I
think about like raw Cloud you know apis
sdks whatever I think about that is that
was Assembly Language right like you can
make a direct API called create ec2 VM
but that's a very lowlevel to operate
then you had tools like terraform which
are like you moved up to python right
you just said I want a VM it's terraform
job to figure out how to create manage
it Mudge the sub 20 API under the hood
the next level up is I don't even want
to really write the python I just want
to write the specification said here's
my Java app it needs a mySQL database it
needs an S3 bucket great it should
generate me my python which I can review
and potentially modify but I don't need
to directly author it and then that's
intermediating me from the Assembly
Language so I think on one dimension
it's we're going to move up the stack in
that order what that enables though is
if I say hey the way I specified my app
day one I going back to the sort of life
cycle was Java app with mySQL with
whatever then now when I start talking
about the day two day three day four
operational activities to your point how
many of those can I now automate away
without breaking the contract you've
given me your contract was this Java app
with my SQL or whatever day two I know
okay there was a I can watch the CBE
list that comes from jdk I know there's
a jdk vulnerability that needs to be
patched so you can look at and say
there's only so many operational
workflows a very key one is things like
patching and Vol management so can I
take something like that which is a huge
chore for most organizations I can
automatically subscribe to the feed of
vulnerabilities or new version releases
of Linux internal or whatever and really
the core should be okay I should be able
to take the app take the new version of
the OS and jdk I can deploy you into a
lower environment like staging I can
look at your observability if nothing
broke your unit test passed metrics look
consistent plus minus some margin I I
then tee it up and give it to the user
and say hey I did the patch here's the
change in the code I ran it in staging
here's the delta in your testing and
your metrics everything looks nominal
plusus 1% do you want to push this
button and merge it to production and I
think a system like that then gives you
the user a lot of control and confidence
because you're not saying I'm going to
go Auto patch prod for you and maybe
blow up your Universe yeah eventually if
you said yes a 100 times and never had
to say no you might say you know what
just go ahead automatically maybe under
these conditions or maybe you segregate
your tier one application maybe my core
bank I would don't whatever my mobile
API okay whatever and so you might tier
at tier one tier two or whatever and
over time you build the confidence but I
think it's like what's the amount of
work when you think about day two
patching every app in the exists in the
world how much of that can I autom make
probably like 99% of it if not 100% of
it and that is a tremendous amount of
value add when you think about just one
very specific thing which is just patch
and vulner management then you think
about right sizing I don't think I've
ever met a developer who right sized any
app ever and it's it's tedious you're
going to deploy the app then you're
going to go look at Telemetry metrics
then you're going to go try a different
size out it's just who's going to do
this right so there's a whole bunch of
automated tools but the whole process of
saying okay I'm going to try it in an
automated way maybe I think I should be
at 5 VMS instead of 10 so I'm going to
increment delete VMS monitor it make
sure nothing breaks it's just tedious
and timec consuming but if the AI could
just do it for me and say hey I saw that
you were underutilized you're at 2% CPU
utilization I right sized you from 10
VMS to five and I stayed within some
guardrail if CPU utilization stays under
50% do you care probably not like that
type of day three right sizing cost
optimization you can probably have it
fully automated so when I start looking
at those day3 day4 type actions it's a
lot of things like that right it's
runbook automation hey you saw my logs
are getting my disc is getting full
based on my data dog observability or
whatever just go run anible
automatically and clear the log files
you don't need to tell me to just go do
it it feels a promising future and it's
interesting it feels like a place in
which a modern startup that creates
themselves can tee themselves up to
automate a bunch of these processes on
it more so than an Enterprise that has a
environment it's a little bit like the
Advent of infrastructures code if you do
it from the beginning you find yourself
in a very different place but once
you've allowed drift to happen not even
drift you've just done a bunch of things
manual it's actually very hard to
Wrangle it back which by the way is
another piece that a bunch of AI develop
startups are trying to do which is I
will read your state in production and I
will generate infrastructure as code to
do that once again needing to be
manually verified that they're correct
but I think I like the the destination
it's clearly very aligned with with what
we do here at tesel and It Gos down to
these small set of things which is I
need a specification that says what is
it that I want to do with a certain
level of degrees of freedom around how
much is within your RIT to decide versus
how much do I want to dictate there is
some generation ability of the actual
code which as we discussed in terraform
especially is is more doable even than
in other types of code and then
eventually when deployed key key key
here is the ability to verify and to see
that nothing broke that it is okay and
and I think that's true in many things
operational but I think what's
interesting in is that the best
practices in this world actually have
handled this not just by understanding
all the variables and anticipating
everything but also through these Canary
releases of hey just apply this to some
small fraction of your traffic and then
monitor to see nothing significantly
deviated and then go on and on and so a
lot of this is around existing best
practices at scale it's just hard to fit
it in if you don't do them all which
sort of smells of digital transformation
type type motion where you really you
have to
go in it's a little bit harder to dable
I think that's 100% right it's the the
way you put it before is that the Divide
between the hav and Have Nots gets wider
and I think the Enterprises that grew up
on itail sort of ticket driven manual
process for them it makes it that much
harder because I think if to your point
it's like the ones that started Dev opsy
native or infrastructure is code native
however you want to think about it but
then the leap into the sort of world
that I'm describing isn't that hard
because the fundamental building blocks
will be the same right at the end of the
day the high level specification will
generate infrastructure as code the
infrastructure's code can also help
synthesize what the higher level
intentions are but if you're starting
from a universe of no intentionality
basically it was just a bunch of tickets
that created a bunch of infrastructure
then yeah there's tools out there that
will reverse engineer but what's always
missing is intent right I can't discern
what's an accidental property of your
environment versus something that was an
intentional property of your environment
was the S3 bucket public because it was
a mistake or you intended it to be
public right there's almost no way right
you're trying to put Humpty Dumpty back
together from a thousand pieces and you
don't know what Humpty ever looked like
yeah and I think and the problem in a
lot of these big Enterprises is nobody
does because this infrastructure has
been running for 30 years and the people
who provisioned it have been retired I
think that's true know again the good
news is AI can slightly help you with
that as well they can go there and autoc
classify and learn a bunch of these
things but it's a process that has to
happen I think so so we've painted the
timeline over here starting from the AI
generated infrastructure as Cod or
summarization on it onto hopefully like
a fairly imminent contextualization of
that generation doesn't feel that far
out for at least sort of the base level
of it and then can evolve into it into
maybe these sort of native autonomous
workflows that maybe they do require
having all the pieces in place to enact
maybe let's talk a little bit about
people just end is what does this all
mean to someone working in this domain
if you're an Sr today versus an SRE in
five years time I don't think it's more
than that I think it's five years would
already be substantial guess what's your
view around the difference in skills you
might need and if you're in that
position right now what would you go
learn and invest in I would say this is
like a three to five year timeline for a
lot of the stuff we're talking about
it's not a 20 year timeline it's
interesting because I think it actually
if you think about what infrastructure
as code did for a lot of sres sort of
moves you out from I'll call it sitting
at the receiving end of a ticketing
queue and saying hey you're going to
manually go orchestrate things to really
what your job is to really design and
assess what the outcome was and then to
some translate that to things like
infrastructure as code and build
Automation and pipelines and things like
that around it so this really does is
actually it's just a longer lever for
those people I think the people who are
already thinking that's what their job
is if my job is design assessment
optimization I'm going to give you a
much longer lever if you think your job
is writing of terraform code or
execution of infrastructure activities
then in many ways some of the stuff will
obviate that right because you'll move
away from really even today we shouldn't
be in a place where we're manually
filing tickets and someone's updating a
firewall rule by hand right a lot of
that happens we still see a ton of that
in industry but really we already have
the tools when you think about things
like infrastructures code that you
shouldn't be doing that the next level
up is should you even write the
infrastructure as code or should you
just manage those set of intents and
specifications so I think from a skill
set perspective what's still relevant is
you have to know the domain you have to
know what a firewall is you have to know
what a VPC is indications that the the
llm might not know as well you have to
know that a public bucket is less secure
than a private bucket okay maybe that's
basic but and more yeah but I think
what's key is it's the domain knowledge
that's valuable of the SR and then
helping focus on an automation driven
approach of how I'm enabling the
business to achieve its outcomes because
infrastructure at the end of the day
nobody cares about infrastructure as an
ends infrastructure is a means
fundamentally so if you put yourself in
that role as an say okay when I'm
delivering is a means for my business to
deliver its applications or to operate
its business or whatever how do I do
that most efficiently through automation
through an upleveling of the
specification and apply a certain domain
knowledge to make sure we're doing in a
way that's secure compliant cost
effective
then this world becomes a much longer
lever for you we had a couple of
conversations on the podcast around the
evolving role of a software developer or
an app Dev in this and talked about
these sort of two routes one which they
go more towards the product management
side and understanding what the business
needs and the other goes more towards
the architect route and and seeing
things a higher level and it's possible
that in the world of sres they need to
do both because really a lot of the work
converges and so they need to have the
domain expertise look at things
architecturally to be able to make those
trade-off decisions through their
subject matter knowledge but also
understand the the motivations of the
business and what are like what is
indeed the current initiative and and
trajectory which I guess I I I hope for
many people is a positive transition but
it is yet another jump for those who
really are CIS admins at their core it
moves them further and further away from
that correct yeah I think that's fair
and I think that notion of when you look
at the very best sres they really are
some combination of a PM and an
architect because that's what they're
doing they're translating the business's
needs and requirements into an
architecture and then into a road map
from the infrastructure perspective and
I think it's you're right that's what
it'll become I think in appdev there's a
stronger distinction between a PM which
is more user customer facing versus an
architect in infrastructure your user
customers the internal app so the
architect and PM are one of the same to
a large extent and I think for the CIS
ad folks I think the nice thing in some
sense is some of these tools will
actually be I a lower learning curve I
would expect than maybe the jump from
CIS admin to infrastructure as code in
some sense was a higher bar because you
have to actually learn a bunch of syns
and learn a new set of tools and
workflows where it's in some sense going
to the AI driven world of it it'll be a
little bit more NLP driven but what
there's no escape from is actually your
value is you still have to understand a
much broader domain if all I was doing
was CIS admin and updating firewall
rules my domain that I understood was a
very small domain you're probably not
going to want an architect that only
knows about fire rules it's a bit too
narrow so I think your scope necessarily
I think I'm giving you a much longer
lever in some sense I expect you to be
live lifting a bigger rock it also feels
like the ability to be data driven or to
understand sort of those broader
implications is important even a sense
of some form of gut feeling around the
types of mistakes that the llm might do
because those are really the two ways in
which you don't get yourself in trouble
when the llm performs or the AI performs
more of the actions is one is be able to
observe that with data and so you
probably need to sharpen that skill even
more than you do today and two is maybe
a little bit anticipatory just like any
experience as will have this sort of
tingling feeling of I think this is
going to cause trouble like I think the
system will not like this choice of
allocation they would benefit from
having some form of of gut fill for how
the LM might respond or act in those
instem like with any technology we work
with and I think a lot of it will come
to process design and what I mean by
that is if you think about hey I test
everything by deploying to prodog
okay You're vulnerable to a whole class
of mistake if that's your process first
if you say hey I have this more
regimented I send it to test then I
promote to Stage then I promote to prod
and we have a data driven validation in
each of those environments or maybe
we're doing traffic shadowing into
staging or whatever there's a process
design aspect of that which actually
would Shield you from a lot of those
types of mistakes in llm might make
because you're going to catch them at an
earlier phase versus YOLO deploy prod we
caught it in prod and it's same thing
with human developer writing code
there's some false positive rate of them
writing errors or whatever you're not
going to catch everything so that's why
we have staging environments so I think
it becomes there's even more pressure on
being that doing that in a bit more of a
rigorous disciplined way where I think
you know some organizations are really
good at it and lots are fairly sloppy
right yeah and I guess the positive sort
of spin on that is that it's more about
automated processes and I think more of
these steps can can pass automatically
in because the hope is that llms take
away the grind take away the the grunt
work that we have to do but they do
require us to understand what we want
better and to define the methodology to
achieve it exactly Arman this was a
great conversation thanks for the the
insights of where the world of
intruction code is going in this with
respect to to Ai and sharing a bunch of
these learnings yeah my pleasure thanks
so much and looking forward to all the
stuff you guys are doing to make some of
this stuff for reality we'll try to help
a little bit with this domain as well
ready for tuning in and I hope you join
us for the next one
[Music]
thanks for tuning in join us next time
on the AI native Dev brought to you by
tessla